<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>How to single cell on Krishnaswamy Lab</title>
    <link>https://dburkhardt.github.io/tutorial/</link>
    <description>Recent content in How to single cell on Krishnaswamy Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Krishnaswamy Lab</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://dburkhardt.github.io/tutorial/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://dburkhardt.github.io/tutorial/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dburkhardt.github.io/tutorial/introduction/</guid>
      <description>As single cell RNA-sequencing experiments become more popular, we keep on hearing a few questions over and over: &amp;ldquo;How should I start analyzing my data?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s the advantage of using PHATE over t-SNE?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;How should I cluster my data?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;How can I identify differentially expressed genes between these two clusters?&amp;rdquo;
High throughput technologies are only a few years old, and there are not many (if any) standards for analyzing a dataset.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1. Preprocessing</title>
      <link>https://dburkhardt.github.io/tutorial/preprocessing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dburkhardt.github.io/tutorial/preprocessing/</guid>
      <description>1.0 Introducing scprep Scprep is a lightweight scRNA-seq toolkit for Python Data Scientists Most scRNA-seq toolkits are written in R, but we develop our tools in Python. Currently, Scanpy is the most popular toolkit for scRNA-seq analysis in Python. In fact, if you&amp;rsquo;d prefer to use that, you can find most of our lab&amp;rsquo;s analytical methods including PHATE and MAGIC in scanpy. However, scanpy has a highly structured framework for data representation and a steep learning curve that is unnescessary for users already comfortable with the suite of methods available in Pandas, Scipy, and Sklearn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2. Visualizing PCA dimensions</title>
      <link>https://dburkhardt.github.io/tutorial/visualizing_pca/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dburkhardt.github.io/tutorial/visualizing_pca/</guid>
      <description>In this section, we&amp;rsquo;re going to go over a few introductory techniques for visualizing and exploring a single cell dataset. This is an essential analysis step, and will tell us a lot about the nature of the data we&amp;rsquo;re working with. We&amp;rsquo;ll figure out things like:
 If the data exists on a trajectory, clusters, or a mix of both How many kinds of cells are likely present in a dataset If there are batch effects between samples If there are technical artifacts remaining after preprocessing  We&amp;rsquo;re going to use two main tools for this analysis: PCA and PHATE.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3. Visualizing data using PHATE</title>
      <link>https://dburkhardt.github.io/tutorial/visualizing_phate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dburkhardt.github.io/tutorial/visualizing_phate/</guid>
      <description>Once you&amp;rsquo;ve inspected the principle components of your dataset, it&amp;rsquo;s time to start visualizing your data using PHATE. We&amp;rsquo;re going to demonstrate PHATE analysis on a few datasets. We will show:
 How PHATE works
 Running PHATE on several datasets
 How to interpret a PHATE plot
 Clustering using the diffusion potential How to pick parameters for PHATE
 How to troubleshoot common issues with PHATE plots</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>